Rauschning, Hermann; Papers ger076
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Hermann Rauschning Papers
1930-1980
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger076
1.2 cubic ft.
The collection contains correspondence and publications of Hermann Rauschning.
Collection X
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The provenance of this collection is unknown.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is processed and organized chronologically. There are no series.
Historical Note
Hermann Rauschning was president of the Free City of Danzig and a onetime Nazi. He emigrated to the United States, became a farmer in Oregon, and wrote on National Socialism and his own political career.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence (copies) of Hermann Rauschning with Golo Mann, Karl O. Paetel, Eugen Rosenstock Huessy, Dorothy Thompson, and others; publications by Rauschning; and newspaper clippings with articles by and about Rauschning.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred the following monographs all authored by Hermann Rauschning: Die Deutsche Einheit und der Weltfriede, Die Konservative Revolution, Gespräche mit Hitler, Gespräche mit Hitler, Hitler Bizalmasa Voltam,Ist Friede Noch Möglich?,L'Allemagne Entre L'Ouest Et L'Est, La Germania Fra L' Occidente E L'Oriente, Masken und Metamorphosen des Nihilismus, Mluvil jsem s Hitlerem, Mut zu einer Neuen Politik, Tiyd Van Delirium to the book division of Special Collections. They will be catalogued and included in the University Library Catalog.
Germany -- History -- 1933-1945
- Articles About Rauschning - Germany, 1930-1977; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Publication - The Argus Press - "Hitler Wants the World" - Hermann Rauschning, 1941 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles by Rauschning - USA, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - Heinrich Brüning, 1941; 1946; 1953; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Articles About Rauschning - England, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Articles About Rauschning - USA, 1941-1942; 1946-1949; 1955; 1972; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence - Rolf Gardiner, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Publication - The Christian Century - "The Church and the Post War Task" - Hermann Rauschning, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Publication - Maclean's Canada National Magazine - "What To Do With Germany" - Hermann Rauschning, 1944 (Flat-file 1)
- Correspondence - Gottfried Reinhold Treviranus, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Articles by Rauschning - Europe, 1945; 1949; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- General Correspondence, 1945; 1959; 1976; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence - Louis Lochner, 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence - Dorothy Thompson, 1945-1959; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence - Hans Joachim Schoeps, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence - Eugene Rosenstock - Huessy, 1950; 1956; 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence - Ernst Jaegar, 1950-1953; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence - Arnold Krieger, Tina Krieger, Hans Sedlmayr, 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Publications - Sonderdruck Universitas, 1952 May-1952 June (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Publication - Merian - "Die Heimsuchung" - Hermann Rauschning, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Publications - Geo Politik, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Publication - Press Universitaire Romande - "La Fanction de L'Europe dans un Monde en Paix" - Hermann Rauschning, 1953 December (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Publication - Sonderdruck aus dem Jahrbuch der Ranke-Gesellschaft - "Thesen zu einem Vortrag über den Nationalsozialismus als Geschichtliches Problem" - Hermann Rauschning, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Correspondence - Karl O. Paetel, 1954-1957; 1962-1967; 1971; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Publications - Widerstandsrecht und Grenzen der Staatsgewalt "Die Heutige Position - Staats - und Rechtsphilosophisch" - Hermann Rauschning, 1955 June (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Articles by Rauschning - Rheinisch-Westfaelische Nachrichten, 1955; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence - Bernt Von Heiseler, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence - Eugene Gerstenmaier, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Correspondence - Martin Fischer, 1956-1980; Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Publications - Neue Politik, 1957; 1959; 1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Correspondence - Rudolf Pectrel, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Correspondence - Gustav Heireman, 1957-1972; Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1960 February-1960 June (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1960 July-1960 November (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Publication - Kommunität - Vierteljahrscheft - Der Evangelischen Akademie "Die Mitte - Mut zu Politik" - Hermann Rauschning, 1960 October (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1961 January-1961 April (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1961 July-1961 December (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1962 February-1962 July (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1962 August-1962 November (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Correspondence - Golo Mann, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1963 March-1963 December (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Publications - Blätter für Deutsche und Internationale Politik, 1964 August-1964 September (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Publications - The Dalhousie Review - "War and Politics in Germany" - Hermann Rauschning, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Publications - Sonderdruck aus Ernst Nolte - "Die Revolution des Nihilismus" - Hermann Rauschning, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)